Thank you very much. Good evening.
شكراً جزيلاً. مساء الخير.
Some of you may have noticed that my last name is Nutt.
ربما لاحظ البعض منكم أن اسمي العائلي هو (نات).
And if you did, you are forgiven for wondering
إن كنت قد فعلت، فأنت معفي عن التساؤل
how a Nutt managed to end up in a war zone.
كيف انتهى المطاف ب (نات) في منطقة حرب.
I actually was offered, right out of medical school, and accepted
في الواقع، لقد عُرِضَ عليَّ عقب تخرجي من كلية الطب، وقد قبلت بذلك،
a volunteer contract to work with UNICEF in war-torn Somalia,
عقد عمل تطوعي لكي أعمل مع اليونسيف في الصومال التي مزقتها الحرب،
that was worth one dollar.
وقد كانت قيمة العقد دولاراً واحداً.
And, you see, I had to be paid this dollar
وكما تعلمون، يجب أن يُدْفَعَ لي هذا الدولار
in the event that the UN needed to issue an evacuation order,
في حال ما اقتضى الأمر أنْ تُصْدِرَ الأمم المتحدة أوامر بالإخلاء،
so that I would be covered.
فسيشملني ذلك الإجراء.
I was, after all, heading into one of the world's most dangerous places.
فوق كل ذلك، كنت حينها في طريقي إلى واحدة من أخطر الأماكن في العالم.
And by now, some of you may be asking yourselves,
الآن، ربما يتساءل البعض منكم،
and I just want to reassure you,
وأودُّ فقط أن أؤكد لكم،
that I did get half the money up front.
أنني تسلمت نصف المبلغ مقدماً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But you see, this is how, with 50 cents in my pocket,
ولكن كما ترون، مع خمسين سنتاً في جيبي،
I ended up in Baidoa, Somalia.
هكذا انتهى بي المطاف في منطقة بيدوا في الصومال.
Journalists called it the "city of death."
أطلق عليها الصحافييون اسم "مدينة الموت".
And they called it the city of death
وأطلقوا عليها مدينة الموت
because 300,000 people had lost their lives there --
لأن 300,000 شخص لقوا حتفهم في تلك المدينة،
300,000 people,
300,000 شخص،
mostly as a result of war-related famine and disease.
نتيجةً للمجاعة والأمراض المرتبطة بالحرب غالباً.
I was part of a team that was tasked with trying to figure out
كنت ضمن فريق أسندت له مهمة محاولة معرفة
how best to respond to this humanitarian catastrophe.
أفضل الطرق للحد من هذه الكارثة الإنسانية.
It was right on the heels of the Rwandan genocide,
كنا على أعتاب إبادة جماعية شبيهة بما حدث في رواندا،
and aid money to the region was drying up.
وقد كان مال المساعدات الموجه للإقليم على وشك النفاد.
Many aid organizations, unfortunately,
للأسف، عدد كبير من منظمات الإغاثة،
had been forced to close their doors.
أُجْبِرَتْ على إغلاق أبوابها.
And so the question that I was asked to specifically help answer,
لذلك كان السؤال الذي طُلِبَ مني الإجابة عليه على وجه الخصوص،
which is one that aid workers ask themselves in war zones the world over,
هو السؤال الذي يطرحه عمال الإغاثة في كل مكان على أنفسهم في مناطق الحرب،
is: What the hell do we do now?
ألا وهو: ما الذي نفعله الآن بحق الجحيم؟
You know, the security environment in Somalia at that moment in time --
كما تعرفون، كانت البيئة الأمنية في الصومال حينها ـ
and nothing has really changed too much --
ولم يحدث تغيير كبير في الحقيقة ـ
can best be described as "Mad Max" by way of "A Clockwork Orange."
أفضل ما توصف به هو فيلم "ماد ماكس" بطريقة فيلم "أكلوكورك أورانج."
And I remember very distinctly a couple of days after my arrival,
وأتذكر بوضوح أنه بعد بضعة أيام من وصولي،
I went up to a feeding clinic.
ذهبت إلى عيادة تغذية.
There were dozens of women who were standing in line,
كانت هناك العشرات من النساء يقفن في صف،
and they were clutching their infants very close.
حيث كن يمسكن بأطفالهن عن قرب.
About 20 minutes into this conversation I was having
قضيت حوالي 20 دقيقة من الحوار
with this one young woman,
مع هذه المرأة الشابة،
I leaned forward
انحنيت إلى الأمام
and tried to put my finger in the palm of her baby's hand.
وحاولت وضع إصبعي في راحة يد طفلتها.
And when I did this,
وعندما فعلت ذلك،
I discovered that her baby was already in rigor.
اكتشفت أن طفلتها متيبسة الأعضاء سلفاً.
She was stiff,
كانت متيبسة،
and her little, lifeless hand was curled into itself.
وقد كانت يدها الصغيرة الهامدة مغلقة على نفسها.
She had died hours before
فقد ماتت قبلها بساعات
of malnutrition and dehydration.
نتيجة لسوء التغذية والجفاف.
I later learned that as her baby was dying,
علمت لاحقاً أنه بينما كانت طفلتها تحتضر،
this young woman had been held for two days
كانت هذه المرأة محبوسة لمدة يومين
by some teenage boys who were armed with Kalashnikov rifles,
من قبل أولاد مراهقين مسلحين ببنادق الكلاشنكوف،
and they were trying to shake her down for more money,
وكانوا يحاولون إخضاعها بحثاً عن مزيد من المال،
money she very clearly did not have.
الذي كان من الواضح أنها لم تكن تملكه.
And this is a scene that I have confronted
وهذا هو المشهد الذي واجهته
in war zones the world over;
في مناطق الحرب في كل مكان؛
places where kids, some as young as eight -- they are this big --
أماكن يوجد بها أطفال، بعضهم في الثامنة من العمر، بهذا السن الكبير
and those kids, they have never been to school.
ولم يلتحقوا بالمدرسة على الإطلاق.
But they have fought and they have killed with automatic rifles.
ولكنهم قاتلوا وقَتلوا باستخدام البنادق الآلية.
Is this just the way the world is?
هل هذه هي الطريقة التي يسير بها العالم؟
Some will you tell you that war is unavoidably human.
سيخبرك أحدهم أن الحرب بفعل الإنسان دوماً.
After all, it is as old as existence itself.
فوق كل ذلك، هي قديمة قدم الحياة نفسها.
We say never again, and yet it happens again and again and again.
نقول لا للحرب، ولكنها مع ذلك تحدث مراراً وتكراراً.
But I will tell you that I have seen the absolute worst
لكنني سأخبركم أنني شهدت الأسوأ على الإطلاق
of what we as human beings are capable of doing to one another,
لما بمقدورنا كبشر أن نفعله بالآخرين،
and yet I still believe a different outcome is possible.
ولكنني ما زلت أؤمن بحدوث نتيجة مختلفة.
Do you want to know why?
أتودون أن تعرفوا السبب؟
Because over 20 years of doing this work,
لأنه بعد أكثر من 20 عاماً قضيتها في هذا العمل،
going in and out of war zones around the world,
متجولة في مناطق الحرب حول العالم،
I have come to understand
توصلت للفهم
that there are aspects of this problem
بأن لهذه المشكلة أبعاداً
that we, all of us, as people occupying this shared space,
يمكننا، جميعاً، كبشر نشغل هذه المساحة المشتركة،
that we can change --
يمكننا أن نحدث تغييراً--
not through force or coercion or invasion,
دون اللجوء للقوة أو الإكراه أو الغزو،
but by simply looking at all of the options available to us
لكن ببساطة بالنظر إلى كل الخيارات المتاحة لنا
and choosing the ones that favor peace at the expense of war,
واختيار تلك التي تحبّذ السلام على حساب الحرب،
instead of war at the expense of peace.
بدلاً عن الحرب على حساب السلام.
How so?
كيف ذلك؟
Well, I want you to consider this:
حسناً، أريد منكم أخذ الآتي بعين الإعتبار:
there are at least 800 million small arms and light weapons
يوجد على الأقل 800 مليون قطعة سلاح صغيرة وأخرى خفيفة
in circulation in the world today.
متداولة حول العالم اليوم.
The vast majority of civilians, like that young baby,
الغالبية العظمى من المدنيين، مثل ذلك الطفل الصغير،
who are dying in war zones around the world,
الذين يلقون حتفهم في مناطق الحرب حول العالم،
are dying at the hands of various armed groups
يموتون على يد مجموعات مسلحة عديدة
who rely on a near-infinite supply of cheap, easy and efficient weapons
والتي تعتمد على دعم شبه لا نهائي من الأسلحة الرخيصة والسهلة والفعالة
to rape, threaten, intimidate and brutalize those civilians
لاغتصاب وتهديد وإرعاب والبطش بهؤلاء المدنيين
at every turn.
عند كل منعطف.
How cheap?
إلى أي درجة هي رخيصة؟
Well, in some parts of the world,
حسناً، في بعض أنحاء العالم،
you can buy an AK-47 for as little as 10 dollars.
يمكنك شراء بندقية طراز AK-47 بمبلغ زهيد يعادل 10 دولارات.
In many places in which I have worked,
في كثير من المناطق التي عملت بها،
it is easier to get access to an automatic rifle
من السهولة بمكان الحصول على بندقية آلية
than it is to get access to clean drinking water.
من أن تحصل على ماء عذب للشرب.
And so now the important part:
والآن الجزء المهم:
Can anything be done about this?
هل من طريقة لوقف هذا الأمر؟
To answer that question,
للإجابة على ذلك السؤال،
let's take a look at this map of the world.
دعونا نلقي نظرة على خريطة العالم هذه.
And now, let's add in all of the countries that are currently at war,
دعونا الآن نضيف إليها جميع الدول التي ترزح تحت نيران الحرب،
and the number of people who have either died
وعدد الأشخاص الذين إما لقوا حتفهم
or have been displaced as a result of that violence.
أو شُرّدوا كنتيجة لذلك العنف.
It is a staggering number --
إنه رقم مذهل--
more than 40 million people.
أكثر من 40 مليون شخص.
But you will also notice something else about this map.
ولكنكم ستلاحظون شيئاً آخر يتعلق بهذه الخريطة.
You will notice that most of those countries
ستلاحظون أن أغلب تلك الدول
are in the Global South.
تقع في جنوب الكرة الأرضية.
Now, let's look at the countries
الآن، فلنلق نظرة على الدول
that are the world's top 20 exporters of small arms in the world.
التي تعدّ أكبر 20 مصدر للأسلحة الصغيرة في العالم.
And what do we notice?
ماذا نلاحظ؟
Well, you see them in green.
حسناً، هي تلك باللون الأخضر.
You will notice that those are mostly countries in the Global North,
ستلاحظون أن أغلبها دول تقع في شمال الكرة الأرضية،
primarily Western countries.
هي في المقام الأول دول غربية.
What does this tell us?
ما الذي يعنيه لنا هذا؟
This tells us that most of the people who are dying in war
يعني لنا هذا أن أغلب من يموتون في الحرب
are living in poor countries,
يعيشون في دول فقيرة،
and yet most of the people who are profiting from war
وأن أغلب من يستفيدون من الحرب
are living in rich countries -- people like you and me.
يعيشون في دول غنية-- أشخاص مثلي ومثلكم.
And then what if we go beyond small arms for a second.
ماذا لو تجاوزنا أمر الأسلحة الصغيرة للحظة.
What if we look at all weapons in circulation in the world?
ماذا لو ألقينا نظرة على مجمل الأسلحة المتداولة حول العالم؟
Who does the biggest business?
من يقوم بالعمل الحقيقي؟
Well, roughly 80 percent of those weapons
حسناً، تقريباً 80% من تلك الأسلحة
come from none other than the five permanent members
تأتي من الدول الخمس الأعضاء
of the United Nations Security Council,
في مجلس الأمن التابع للأمم المتحدة،
plus Germany.
بالإضافة إلى ألمانيا.
It's shocking, isn't it?
إنه شيء صادم، أليس كذلك؟
Now, some of you might be saying at this moment in time,
ربما يقول البعض منكم الآن،
"Oh yeah, but OK, hang on a second there ... Nutt."
"نعم، لكن حسناً، انتظري للحظة...(نات)."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Grade school was spectacular for me.
كانت المدارس الابتدائية مذهلة بالنسبة لي.
It was, really, a wonderful experience.
كانت تجربةً رائعةً بحق.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But you might be saying to yourselves,
لكن ربما تقولون لأنفسكم،
You know, all of these weapons in war zones -- they're not a cause,
تعلمين أن كل هذه الأسلحة في مناطق الحرب-- ليست هي السبب،
but an effect of the violence that plagues them
بل هي نتيجة للعنف الذي ابتليت به
each and every single day.
في كل يوم وحين.
You know, places like Iraq and Afghanistan,
كما تعلمون، أماكن مثل العراق وأفغانستان،
where they need these weapons to be able to maintain law and order,
حيث هم في حاجة لهذه الأسلحة لفرض سطوة القانون وإحلال النظام،
promote peace and security, to combat terror groups --
تعزيز السلام والأمن لمجابهة الجماعات الإرهابية -
surely this is a good thing.
بالتأكيد هذا شيء جيد.
Let's take a look at that assumption for just one moment,
دعونا نلقي نظرة على ذلك الافتراض للحظة،
because you see there has been a boom in the small-arms trade
لأنه كما ترون حدثت طفرة في تجارة الأسلحة الصغيرة
since the start of the War on Terror.
منذ بدء الحرب على الإرهاب.
In fact, it is a business that has grown threefold
في الواقع، نما العمل في هذا المجال لثلاثة أضعاف
over the past 15 years.
خلال الخمس عشرة سنة الماضية.
And now let's compare that to the number of people
دعونا نقارن ذلك بعدد الناس
who have directly died in armed conflict around the world
الذين لقوا حتفهم بصورة مباشرة في الصراعات المسلحة حول العالم
in that same period.
في نفس تلك الفترة.
What do you notice?
ماذا تلاحظون؟
Well, you notice that, in fact, that also goes up
حسناً، تلاحظون أنه، في الواقع، يرتفع ذلك أيضاً
roughly three- to fourfold.
تقريباً من ثلاثة إلى أربعة أضعاف.
They basically go up and end at the same point.
يرتفع ذلك أساساً وينتهي في نفس النقطة.
Now, we can have a circular argument here
الآن، يمكننا أن نخوض جدالاً لا ينتهي
about whether this increase in fatalities is a response
حول ما إذا كانت زيادة النكبات هذه هي رد فعل
to the increase of small arms, or the other way around.
على زيادة تداول الأسلحة الصغيرة، أو العكس.
But here's what we should really take away from this.
ولكن إليكم ما يجب علينا الخروج به حقاً من هذا الأمر.
What we should take away from this
ما نخرج به من هذا الأمر
is that this is a relationship worth scrutinizing,
هو أن هذه علاقة تستحق التدقيق،
especially when you consider that small arms that were shipped to Iraq
خاصةً، عندما تأخذ بعين الاعتبار أن الأسلحة الصغيرة التي تم شحنها للعراق
for use by the Iraqi Army,
ليستخدمها الجيش العراقي،
or to Syria for so-called moderate opposition fighters,
أو إلى سوريا لمصلحة ما يسمى بمقاتلي المعارضة المعتدلة،
that those arms, many of them, are now in the hands of ISIS;
تلك الأسلحة، أغلبها، هي الآن في يد تنظيم الدولة الإسلامية؛
or when you consider that arms that were shipped to Libya
أو عندما تأخذ بعين الاعتبار أن الأسلحة التي شحنت إلى ليبيا
are now actively drifting across the Sahel,
تتدفق الآن بغزارة عبر منطقة الساحل،
and ending up with groups like Boko Haram and al Qaeda
وينتهي بها المطاف في أيدي مجموعات مثل بوكو حرام وتنظيم القاعدة
and other militant groups.
ومجموعات مسلحة أخرى.
And therein lies the problem.
وهنا تكمن المشكلة.
Because, you see,
لأنه، كما ترون،
small arms anywhere are a menace everywhere,
الأسلحة الصغيرة في أي مكان تمثل الخطر في كل مكان،
because their first stop is rarely their last.
لأن محطتها الأولى نادراً ما تكون الأخيرة.
Spending on war per person per year
حجم الإنفاق على الحرب للفرد سنوياً
now amounts to about 249 dollars --
يعادل حالياً 249 دولار --
249 dollars per person,
249 دولار نصيب الفرد،
which is roughly 12 times what we spend on foreign aid,
وهو ما يعادل تقريباً 12 ضعف إنفاقنا على المساعدات الأجنبية،
money that is used to educate and vaccinate children
وهو المال المستخدم لتعليم وتوفير اللقاحات للأطفال
and combat malnutrition in the Global South.
ولمحاربة سوء التغذية في جنوب الكرة الأرضية.
But we can shift that balance.
لكن يمكننا تحويل هذا التوازن.
How do we do this?
كيف نقوم بذلك؟
Well, it is essentially a problem of both supply and demand,
حسناً، هي مشكلة تتعلق أساساً بالعرض والطلب،
so we can tackle it from both sides.
لذلك، يمكننا معالجة الأمر من كلا الجانبين.
On the supply side,
في ما يخص العرض،
we can push our governments
يمكننا الضغط على حكوماتنا
to adopt international arms transparency mechanisms
لاعتماد آليات شفافية عالمية لتجارة الأسلحة
like the Arms Trade Treaty,
مثل معاهدة تجارة الأسلحة،
which makes it so that rich countries have to be more accountable
الأمر الذي يجعل الدول الغنية أكثر عرضة للمساءلة
for where their arms are going
في ما يتعلق بأين تذهب أسلحتها
and what their arms might be used for.
وفي ماذا سوف تستخدم هذه الأسلحة.
Here in the United States,
هنا في الولايات المتحدة،
the largest arms-exporting country in the world by far,
أضخم دولة مصدرة للأسلحة في العالم حتى اللحظة،
President Obama has rightly signed the Arms Trade Treaty,
وقع الرئيس أوباما عن جدارة معاهدة تجارة الأسلحة،
but none of it takes effect, it isn't binding,
ولكنها لم تُنّزل على أرض الواقع، لذلك فهي ليست ملزمة،
until it is approved and ratified by the Senate.
حتى يوافق مجلس الشيوخ ويصادق عليها.
This is where we need to make our voices heard.
هنا حيث يجب أن نصدح بأصواتنا.
You know, the curbing of small arms --
كما تعلمون، فإن كبح جماح تداول الأسلحة الصغيرة --
it's not going to solve the problem of war.
لن يكون كفيلاً بحل مشكلة الحرب.
Increased control mechanisms won't solve that problem.
لن تحل آليات التحكم المتزايدة المشكلة.
But it's an important step in the right direction.
ولكنها خطوة مهمة في الاتجاه الصحيح.
And it's up to all of us who live in those rich countries
والأمر يعود لنا جميعاً، نحن من نعيش في تلك الدول الغنية
to make change here.
لخلق التغييرالمنشود.
What about on the demand side?
ماذا عن جانب الطلب؟
You know, there are generations around the world
كما تعلمون، هناك أجيال حول العالم
who are being lost to war.
ضاعت بسبب الحرب.
It is possible to disrupt that cycle of violence
من الممكن تعطيل دوامة العنف تلك
with investments in education, in strengthening the rule of law
عن طريق الإستثمار في التعليم، وفي تعزيز قبضة القانون
and in economic development, especially for women.
وفي التنمية الاقتصادية بخاصة للنساء.
I have personally seen
رأيت شخصياً
just how incredibly powerful those kinds of efforts can be
القوة المذهلة لما يمكن أن تكون عليه هذه الجهود
around the world.
حول العالم.
But here's the thing:
ولكن هنا شيء آخر:
they take time,
هذه الجهود تستغرق زمناً،
which means for you as individuals, if you want to give,
مما يعني لكم كأفراد، إن أردتم أن تعطوا،
please, by all means do it.
رجاءً، افعلوا ذلك ما استطعتم إليه سبيلاً.
But know that how you give is just as important
ولكن اعلموا أن طريقة عطائكم لا تقل أهمية
as how much you give.
عن مقدار ذلك العطاء.
Regular contributions like monthly contributions
المشاركات المنتظمة مثل المشاركات الشهرية
are a far more effective way of giving,
تعدّ طريقةً فعالةً للعطاء،
because they allow humanitarian organizations
لأن ذلك يسمح للمنظمات الإنسانية
to properly plan and be invested over the long term,
بالتخطيط السليم والاستثمارعلى المدى الطريل،
and to be present in the lives of families who have been affected by war,
ولإظهار ذلك في حياة الأسر المتضررة من الحرب،
wars that many of us, frankly, all too quickly forget.
حروب، بصراحة، ينساها أغلبنا بسرعة.
When I first got on that plane for Somalia as a young doctor,
عندما ذهبت إلى الصومال في أول مرة كطبيبة شابة على متن تلك الطائرة،
I had no idea what it meant to live with war.
لم تكن لدي أدنى فكرة عن ما تعنيه الحياة في وسط الحرب.
But I can tell you that I know what it means now.
ولكن يمكنني الآن أن أخبركم عن ما يعنيه ذلك.
And I know what it means
وأعرف ما يعنيه
to lie in bed in the pitch-black night
أن تستلقي في فراش في الليل الحالك
and listen to that haunting "pop-pop-pop-pop-pop!"
وتستمع إلى ذلك الصوت المؤرق "بوب-بوب-بوب-بوب-بوب!"
of automatic gunfire,
العائد لبندقية آلية،
and wonder with absolute dread
ثم تتساءل في خوف مطلق
how many minutes I have left until it will be right on top of me.
كم من الوقت تبقى لي حتى تصوب تلك إلى رأسي.
I can tell you that it is a terrifying and agonizing fear,
أستطيع أن أقول لكم أنه خوف مرعب ومفجع،
one that millions of people around the world are forced to confront
خوف يضطر ملايين الناس حول العالم لمواجهته
each and every single day,
في كل يوم وحين،
especially children.
خاصةً الأطفال.
Over the years of doing this work,
حلال سنين عملي في هذا المجال،
unfortunately, war has killed far too many people close to me.
للأسف، أزهقت الحرب أرواح العديد من الأشخاص المقربين لي.
And on at least a couple of occasions,
وفي بضعة مناسبات على الأقل،
war has very nearly killed me as well.
كادت الحرب أن تتسبب بمقتلي أيضاً.
But I firmly believe,
ولكنني أؤمن بشدة،
which is why I get up and do what I do every single day,
وهو ما يجعلني أنهض كل يوم لأقوم بما تعودت لقيام به،
that we can make different choices here.
أنه بإمكاننا إحداث تغيير هنا.
Because you see, war is ours,
لأنه كما ترون، الحرب حربنا نحن،
as human beings.
كبشر.
We buy it, sell it, spread it and wage it.
فنحن نشتريها ونبيعها ونعمل على نشرها وشنّها.
We are therefore not powerless to solve it.
لذلك فنحن لسنا عاجزين عن وقفها.
On the contrary,
بل على النقيض،
we are the only ones who can.
نحن الوحيدون القادرون على ذلك.
Thank you very much, and I want to wish you the greatest success.
شكراً لكم جميعاً، وأتمنى لكم كل النجاح.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)